Okay, חג שמח, Chag Sameach, Happy יום ירושלים. Yom Yerushalayim.
Today's דף Daf is דף סא, Daf Samech Aleph, and we pick
up at the top of סא Samech Aleph
about five lines from the bottom—אבל מודה—five aval modeh lines from the
top, that would be really
ahead—אבל מודה לו. Aval modeh lo. And the issue here is that
there's a seeming contradiction in that our משנה Mishnah says that when
you put a עירוב Eiruv outside of a city what you gain
on one side you lose on the other, which basically means that
the city doesn't count against you, whereas we have another משנה Mishnah
that says that it's actually coming up on the bottom of today's
page, that when you start measuring from outside a city and you
hit a city you have to stop in the middle of a
city, which means the city does count against you. So what's the
difference? So the גמרא Gemara says that the difference was whether
the if the city was within the 2000 completely included in the
2000 then it doesn't count against you at all, but if your
2000 ends in the middle of a city then it does count
against you. So that was the answer that the גמרא Gemara gave,
and who gave it, let me see,
רב אידי Rav Idi in the name of רב יהושע בן לוי.
Rav Yehoshua ben Levi.
And
then רב אידי Rav Idi said apparently, oh, I didn't even realize
that,
that when he, right, so he said this over in the name
of רב יהושע בן לוי, Rav Yehoshua ben Levi, and then he
himself said though that this is like דברי נביאות, Divrei Nevi'ut, like
this is like words of prophecy, which presumably means where'd he get
this from? And then the גמרא Gemara tries to demonstrate that actually
it is pretty clear this distinction from the משניות. Mishnayot. Okay, so
yesterday
so it tried to demonstrate it,
and now the גמרא Gemara picks up, it didn't completely demonstrate and
now the
גמרא Gemara says אבל מודה לו תנן. Aval modeh lo tnan. We
never taught in the משנה Mishnah this idea that if you're measuring
and you end in the middle of a city that the city
counts against you. The גמרא Gemara says ולא, V'lo, is that really
true that we didn't teach it, meaning trying to demonstrate why are
you calling this דברי נביאות, Divrei Nevi'ut, it really is pretty clear
this idea in the משנה. Mishnah. והתנן, V'ha tnan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, and it's actually the bottom of today's דף Daf
of today's עמוד, Amud, ולמודד שאמרו נותנין לו אלפים אמה, U'l'modeh she'amru
notnin lo alpaim amah, when the guy starts measuring from outside of
the city he has 2000 אמות, Amot, שאפילו סוף מדתו כלה במערה,
She'afilu sof midato kalah bim'arah, even if the end of the 2000
ends in the middle of a cave, סוף
עיר, Sof eir, סוף מדתו כלה במערה, Sof midato kalah bim'arah, even
if it ends in the middle of a cave you stop in
the middle of a cave. So you see it's pretty explicit that
your 2000 אמות Amot when you're in a city, when you start
outside a city and measure into a city you don't get the
whole city. The גמרא Gemara says fine, you're right, it is clear
that the city counts against you. What's not clear is the circumstances
under which it doesn't count against you. סוף עיר איצטריכא ליה ולא
תנן. Sof ir itztrech leh v'lo tnan. We never taught in a
משנה Mishnah
explicitly that if you actually the entire city was in the 2000
אמות Amot that it did not count against you. Okay, now the
point is this distinction wasn't explicit in the משנה, Mishnah, but at
the end of the day there really is this problem in the
משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah we started with yesterday said, like I
said, if you put the עירוב Eiruv outside of a city everything
you gain on one side you lose on the other, which means
the city doesn't count against you. The next משנה Mishnah we're about
to see, which we just which the גמרא Gemara just referred to,
it says if you're measuring outside a city and you stop in
the middle of a city, then you can't go any further, the
city does count against you. So there's a pretty clear contradiction in
the משניות Mishnayot whether the city does or doesn't. The basis for
the distinction is not explicit. The basis for the distinction is what
רב יהושע בן לוי Rav Yehoshua ben Levi is introducing. Okay, so
that the גמרא Gemara says that's not explicit, that difference. Okay, and
the way he explains the difference is as I said that if
the whole city is within the 2000 it doesn't count against you
and if the 2000 ends in the middle of the city then
it does count against you. Okay, so that's the position of רב
יהושע בן לוי Rav Yehoshua ben Levi to explain the contradiction of
these משניות Mishnayot and by the way that is the way that
we פוסקין, Pasken, דברי נביאות Divrei Nevi'ut or not, and actually it
does sound like the reasonable explanation for this contradiction. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, said
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מאן תני אנשי לא משתבש Man tni anshei
lo mishtabesh ומאן תני אין אנשי לא משתבש. u'man tni ein anshei
lo mishtabesh. So again we're about to have this really going to
the next משנה Mishnah where it says the people of a big
city can walk through the entire small city but the people of
small city cannot walk through the entire big city. That's the גירסא
Girsa of אין אנשי עיר קטנה, Ein anshei ir ktanah, the people
of the small city cannot go through the big city, and some
say אנשי עיר קטנה, Anshei ir ktanah, the people of the small
city can go through the big city. So there's a different גירסא
Girsa of the following משנה Mishnah whether it says the small city
can or cannot go through the big city. So says רב נחמן
Rav Nachman neither way is necessarily in error.
Now he's going to explain how each one makes sense. מאן תני
אנשי לא משתבש, Man tni anshei lo mishtabesh, if you say the
people of the small city can go through the big city, דמוקים
לה בנותן, d'mokim lah b'nosan, that they say you're talking that you
actually put your עירוב Eiruv there.
So again if the scenario what happens to my video?
Right,
so if the scenario is, is that here's your big city, and
let's call it for argument's sake 3000 אמות, amot, and here's your
small city which is 1000 אמות, amot, and there's
900 אמות amot between it. So
one גירסא girsa is, the people of the big city can go
through the small, and the small cannot go through the big, which
means what? That the people of the big city go 900, go
1000, all of that is within their 2000, so it doesn't count
against them, so they get to go another 1100. But the people
of the small city, they go 900 and then they get to
go 1100 and they have to stop there. Okay, that's אין אנשי
עיר קטנה ein anshei ir k'tana can go through the עיר גדולה,
ir gedola, they can go some way but they can't go all
the way through. The version that they can go both ways describes
the scenario differently. It says what?
Is it just relative to which city you're in, right?
Yeah, but it says that what it means is, if people from
this city wanted to make an עירוב Eruv here, right, if you're
here and you want to make your עירוב Eruv here, then you
can become a member of this new city and are entitled to
the entire new city. And similarly, if you're from this city, right,
and you wanted to make your עירוב Eruv here, you're allowed to
become a member of the new city and of the small city
and you get the entire city. So it's really a completely different
point, it's not about a case where you start in your city,
it's your ability to associate, to become part of a new city.
Okay, and that actually is what the rest of the משנה Mishna
says explicitly. As we're going to read the משנה, Mishna, the משנה
Mishna explicitly describes that scenario,
but according to one version that's the second case of the משנה.
Mishna. So let's take a look.
מאן
דתני אנשי לא משתבש, Man de'tani anshei lo mishtabesh, מאן דתני אנשי
לא משתבש, Man de'tani anshei lo mishtabesh, מאן דתני אנשי לא משתבש,
Man de'tani anshei lo mishtabesh, דמוקים לה בנתני, de'mokim lah bi-ntanay, when
it says the big can go in the small, the small can
go in the big, it means you put your עירוב Eruv in
the other city and you became a member of the other city.
ומאן דתני אין אנשי לא משתבש, U-man de'tani ein anshei lo mishtabesh,
and if your גירסא girsa is the small city cannot go through
the big city, דמוקים לה במדוד, de'mokim lah bi-mdud, you didn't put
your עירוב Eruv in the next city, you started in your city
and you were measuring and you got to the middle of the
next city, your 2000 ended in the middle of the next city.
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Chisuroi mechsora v'hachi katani, and it's missing some
words and here's how it should read. And the reason it says
it's missing some words is because the end of the משנה Mishna
explicitly is the case of putting your עירוב Eruv in the other
city, joining the other city. So if you want to say it's
saying here that you can't, it's talking about a different case, the
case when you didn't put your עירוב Eruv in the other city
and you ended in the middle.
Okay, חסורי מחסרא, chisuroi mechsora, it's missing some words, והכי קתני, v'hachi
katani, and here's how it should be read: אנשי עיר גדולה מהלכין
את כל עיר קטנה, Anshei ir gedola mahalchin et kol ir k'tana,
the people of the big city can go the entire small city,
ואין אנשי עיר קטנה מהלכין את כל עיר גדולה, v'ein anshei ir
k'tana mahalchin et kol ir gedola, and the small city cannot go
through the big city. במה דברים אמורים, B'meh devarim amurim, this במה
דברים אמורים b'meh devarim amurim is the words that are being inserted.
Okay, when is this true? במדוד, Bi-mdud, if you're starting in your
native city and you're measuring and you ended in the middle, then
you're stuck if you start in the small city. אבל, Aval, but,
and now this is how the משנה Mishna actually continues: מי שהיה
בעיר גדולה והניח את עירובו בעיר קטנה, mi she-hayah b'ir gedola v'hiniach
et eruvo b'ir k'tana, if you were in the big city and
you put your עירוב Eruv in the small, היה בעיר קטנה והניח
את עירובו בעיר גדולה, hayah b'ir k'tana v'hiniach et eruvo b'ir gedola,
you were in the small and you put in the big, then
מהלך את כולה וחוץ לה אלפים אמה, mahalchin et kula v'chutz lah
alpayim amah, you can go the whole city and 2000. So that
as we'll see, we're about to read it a few lines from
now, is the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna says people of the
big can go in the small, small can or cannot go in
the big, and then it describes the scenario of putting your עירוב
Eruv in the opposite city. So the one that says that the
גירסא girsa is that the small cannot, it says that the משנה
Mishna is a contrast. It says if you started in A, then
you cannot go all the way through B, you have to end
there. But if you put your עירוב Eruv in B, then you're
entitled to go through all of B. Okay, so the משנה Mishna
actually describes the scenario of putting your עירוב, Eruv, but this read
says it starts by saying without the עירוב Eruv you're stuck. With
the עירוב Eruv that entitles you to go all the way through
B.
Did they fix up the Mishna?
Yeah,
they added the words that if it says can't go through, it
means can't go through assuming you didn't put an עירוב, Eruv, but
if you did, that's the end of the משנה. Mishna. Those words
were inserted. Yeah, and we'll see that, we're about to read the
משנה Mishna in a few lines. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רב יוסף אמר רמי בר אבא אמר רב
הונא: Amar Rav Yosef amar Rami bar Abba amar Rav Huna: עיר
שיושבת על שפת הנחל, Ir she-yoshevet al sfat ha-nachal, if you have
a city that's right at the edge of a river,
or נחל nachal could mean also a wadi, אם יש לפניה דקה
ארבעה, im yesh lefaneha daka arba-ah, if it's got some type of
a barrier, a דקה daka of four. Now ארבעה arba-ah before we
meant four טפחים tefachim and here even spelled out ארבעה arba-ah means
four טפחים tefachim but we're going to revise that in a minute.
מודדין לה משפת הנחל. Modedin lah mi-sfat ha-nachal. Then it's like any
city and you can count from the edge of the city, from
where the edge of the wadi. ואם לאו *ve'im lav* and if
not אין מודדין לה אלא מפתח ביתו *ein modidin lah ela mipetach
beito*. You do not get, it doesn't get treated as a city,
they're treated as individual houses, and you could only measure from each
person's individual house. Why is this? So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* basically says
you'll remember that a גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* earlier spoke about what happens
if everybody lives in these like thatch huts, and at a certain
point if it's not considered to be like established enough, permanent enough,
if it's all very nomadic, then it's not really considered a city,
every house is considered to be just by itself. So here the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says that apparently if you're right at the edge
of a ואדי *wadi* and you don't have some like what's called
a retaining wall or something, then your whole presence in this city
is very tentative, like we're afraid everybody's going to slide off and
going to collapse, and it's not really considered stable enough of a
presence to be considered a city. So you need to have that
wall, that retaining wall to protect you from the edge of the
river or the edge of the ואדי *wadi*. It's pretty interesting, sort
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* getting into the whole city planning and
making these assessments about what you need to be considered to be
your like stable city.
Okay, thinking about יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* in
אנשי שרון *Anshei Sharon*, אנשי שרון *Anshei
Sharon*, yeah, בתיהם קבריהם *bateihem kivreihem*.
So is that not considered stable? I don't know, that's a good
question, but that's about, I don't know, sort of weather as opposed
to I guess the actual land that they're on, but it's an,
yeah, I doubt it, I doubt I doubt that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* would have gone that far, but you know, again you don't
know where to draw the line. Okay, so it says like this,
so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*,
so אביי *Abaye* said in response to this, in this case דקה
ארבע אמות arba amot, *dakah arba amot* אמרת לן *amart lan*. He
said to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, who was אביי *Abaye*'s רבי Rebbe
*Rebbe*, he said, you know when you first told it to us
you didn't say ארבעה *arba'ah*, four טפחים *tefachim*, you said ארבע *arba*,
four, four אמות amot, *amot*, but the barrier has to be four
אמות amot *amot*. מאי שנא מכל דקי דעלמא דארבעה *mai shna mikol
daki de'alma de'arba'ah*? So, and
so why is it different than all other kinds where it's four
טפחים *tefachim*? So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to
him, התם לא lo, בעיתא תשמישתא *hatam lo bi'ita tashmishta*. Normally you're
not afraid to use the space, so four טפחים *tefachim* is enough,
remember like we had it before to say that
this חצר *chatzer* wasn't part of a מבוי *mavoi*, it was just
to sort of signify your, not, your disconnecting yourself from the surrounding
environment and was much more symbolic. הכא *hacha* here, בעיתא תשמישתא *bi'ita
tashmishta*, without a serious wall you're afraid to use the space, so
therefore it has to be much more functional and much less about
being symbolic, and therefore you need it to really be functional. Okay,
so what we've introduced here is this new idea that if the
city is in a precarious situation without doing some type of a
wall or something to stabilize it, it doesn't count as a city.
So אמר רב יוסף *amar Rav Yosef*, said רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*,
מנא אמינא לה *minan amina lah*? Where do I get this idea
that you have to stabilize a city or else it doesn't count?
דתניא *detanya* we taught in a ברייתא Braita. *Baraita*, התיר רבי Rebbe
שיהיו בני גדגדר יורדים לחמתן ואין בני חמתן עולים לגדגדר *hitir Rebbi
sheyihiyu bnei gadgader yordim lachamtan ve'ein bnei chamtan olim legadgader*. So if
you see רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has a nice little picture, there are
two cities, they're on a slope, they're together on a mountain, גדגדר
*gadgader* is higher and חמתן *chamtan* is lower, and it said רבי
Rebbe, *Rebbi* allowed the people of גדגדר *gadgader* to go down to
חמתן *chamtan* but not the people of חמתן *chamtan* to go to
גדגדר *gadgader*. Okay, so here is your mountain,
okay, here's the people of גדגדר *gadgader* and here's the people of
חמתן *chamtan*, and רבי Rebbe *Rebbi* said this is okay but that
is no good. So what's the difference? Right, if they're in each
other's תחום techum, *techum*, then one each way should be allowed, so
what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so מאי
טעמא
*mai ta'ama* what's the reason? לאו משום דהני עבדו דקה והני לא
עבדו דקה *lav mishum dehani avdu dakah vehani lo avdu dakah*? Oh
I have the explanation. Not like this isn't in the ברייתא *Baraita*
at all, but he says here's, I figured it out, what happened
is that they're all on a slope, so it's all very precarious,
so these people built up a wall to help, you know, protect
them, and these guys didn't. So this counts as a city. If
it counts as a city, right, you count your two thousand אמות
amot, *amot* from the outer edge, you're able to go down, that's
within two thousand אמות amos. *amot*, let's say that this is, I
don't know, a thousand אמות amos, *amot* between them. Okay, but if
they don't have a wall, it doesn't count as a city. So
if it doesn't count as a city, so these guys, true, can
get up here, but the guys down here cannot, right, because if
it doesn't as a city then everybody has to measure from their
own house. So the people of חמתן *chamtan* cannot, all of them
make it to גדגדר *gadgader*, only the people at the very edge.
So it means not all
of them but some of them.
Some of them can but, right, but here everybody can because
of the advantage of squaring off. So if it's not a city,
if it's not
a city you don't get the squaring off.
Right, so it could be that all of the people in חמתן
*chamtan*,
that's true too if you imagine that squaring off scenario, although again
that gets to the question if by squaring off it overlaps does
it work, can it work only in one direction or would it
necessarily work in two? But yes, but you could also get to
the squaring off issue, but that's not how he's explain, well you're
saying he, that could be part of it, if it has a
city it gets that additional benefit of the squaring off, that's true.
So that's how he explains it, that it's based on this idea
that if it's in a precarious situation it does not have the
status of a city, it does not have the status of a
city. Of course the ברייתא *Baraita* is very, is very, you know,
open-ended, like it's very unclear what the distinction is, so it's really
open. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to have a couple
of other interpretations.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: כי אתא רב דימי Rav
Dimi. אמר *Ki Ata Rav Dimi Amar*, when רב דימי *Rav Dimi*
came, he said: Here's the difference. תתרוגי מיתתרוגי להו בני גדר Geder
לבני חמתן *Tatrogei metatregi lehu bnei Gader livnei Chamatan*. The people of
גדר Geder *Gader* were attacking, were at war with the people of
חמתן *Chamatan*. So, really, what he says is interesting, technically they could
have gone either one to another cities, they were all within the
עירוב eruv *eiruv*. But רבי Rebbe *Rebbe* was not doing sort of
his function as a פוסק *posek*, but more as his function as
a, you know, as some type of a political leader and therefore
he wanted to keep them separate. Okay, and therefore he didn't allow
them. So the obvious question's going to be why did he allow
one direction and not the other? And why דווקא *davka* on שבת
Shabbat. *Shabbos*? So, what? Well, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
going to say. So let's take a look. So, ומאי התיר *u'mai
hitir*, what does it mean he allowed? התקין *Hitkin*, it means he
made a תקנה *takana*, not פסקן pasken *pasken*, but he made a
תקנה *takana*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to try to
understand why do you allow one side to go and not the
other direction? So it says, ומאי שנא שבת Shabbos *u'mai shna Shabbos*,
first of all, if you don't want them to go to one
another city, why דווקא *davka* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*? You know, what
does it have to do with... with תחומין *t'chumin*? So of course
it's like that famous story that they asked רב משה *Rav Moshe*,
are you allowed to listen to like recorded music during the ספירה
*Sefirah*? So he said no. So they said, well why? I mean
you know, it's recorded, it's not live. He says, look, I don't
think you're allowed to listen to music the whole year, but nobody
listens to me the rest of the year.
So at least maybe on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* they'll listen to me.
But no, but that isn't what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: דשכיחי בשכרות *de'shchichi beshichrus*,
that שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* everybody is drinking a lot of wine so
they get drunk, so then you sort of act out, it's like
you know, what is it in England during those ball games or
something. Anyway when you're drinking, okay I shouldn't have made it. Anyway,
soccer games they have those like major things. Anyway when you're drinking
you act out on your... on your aggression. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, okay, so כי אזלי להתם נמי ליתתרוגי להו *ki azlei
l'hasam nami letitragi
lehu*? So if that's true, so when the people of גדר Geder.
*Gader* go down into חמתן *Chamatan*, they would also be attacking them.
No, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: כלבא בלא מתייה שב שנין לא
נבח *kalba belo mataye shev shanin lo navach*, a dog not in
its own city for seven years won't bark. So basically even though
the people of גדר *Gader* are the aggressors, if they're not on
their home turf, they're not going to be, you know, they're not
going to act out on it. But if they're the aggressors and
they're on their home turf and the people of חמסון *Chamson* are
the visitors, then they're really, you know, then they're really in danger.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: השתא נמי ליתתרוגי בני חמסון לבני
גדר *hashta nami letitragi bnei Chamson livnei Gader*? Okay, but is that
true? If it's about home turf, why aren't we afraid that the
people of חמסון *Chamson* will attack the people of גדר *Gader* that
are in their city? So it says: כולי האי לא כייפי להו
*kulei hai lo kaifi lehu*, no, that much they're not going to
be
subjected, means still the people of גדר *Gader* are the more powerful
and the more aggressive, they just won't act on it if they're
visitors as opposed to if it's their home turf. So according to
this it is a completely sort of political issue, not הלכות שבת
Shabbos *Hilchos Shabbos* at all, that the people, he did not want
the people of חמסון *Chamson* visiting גדר *Gader* on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*.
He thought that it was a very dangerous situation and therefore forbade
it. Yes, רב גפני *Rav Gafni*? Were they Babylonian? They got to
be Jewish because they're listening to רבי *Rebbe*'s תקנות *takanot* and because
it's said in the... what?
It's רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*.
No, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* is explaining why רבי *Rebbe* made this
הלכה *halacha*. This is a רבי *Rebbe* in a ברייתא *Baraita*.
And these were two Jewish
cities in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*
are killing each
other?
Yeah, I have no idea. What does science say?
גדר *Gader* was mostly inhabited by Gentiles.
Okay, but it still wouldn't explain... oh so if that were true,
it could explain why the people of חמסון *Chamson* would listen to
him and not go to גדר *Gader*. Meaning he
couldn't stop גדר *Gader* going to חמתן *Chamatan* because גדר *Gader* were
non-Jews, they wouldn't have listened to him, but he could have stopped
it the other way I guess.
The Jews might have been very assimilated and not listening anyway.
Right,
and on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and they're drinking. Yeah, you get the
sense they keep שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*.
Right, right, and drinking on
שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*.
Right, I know, it sounds like they're Jewish cities. Yeah, I mean
how else would he have any authority?
Two Jewish cities ever killing each other?
Well you know, I mean there was a lot in the previous
generation, I mean like in the time of the... obviously there was
a lot of a tremendous amount of infighting particularly right around the
time of the חורבן *churban*, but it's true, this is a good
130 years or so after that, so yeah. Yeah, I don't know,
it's true, it is a like a disturbing scenario that it's describing.
Okay, so that's a totally different answer. So now the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: רב ספרא Rav Safra אמר *Rav Safra amar*, רב
ספרא *Rav Safra* says you're making this whole thing too confusing. Or
not confusing, anyway he
says you don't have to introduce this idea of a retaining wall.
Here's the explanation: עיר ir העשויה כקשת הוי *ir ha'asuya k'keshes havi*,
it was a city that was made like a rainbow. So who
cares? Well, here's the way I'll give it, tell you the way
תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* explains it which is a lot easier than the
way
רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* explains it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that if you've
got your rainbow, okay, and you've got your other city here. Now
if the rainbow actually is, you know, within 4,000 אמות amos *amot*
it's all considered to be one city, right? So it's all one
city, so the people in here are all one city, so therefore...
even the people like way up here, you know, da-da-da-da-da, that's all
considered within the city, and then they can get to, you know,
I don't know, let's say it's a thousand אמות, amos and then
they can get here, and this is a thousand אמות, amos and
they can go the whole city. שלום על ישראל, Shalom Al Yisrael,
right? That's for the people up here. That would be the people
of גדר to go to חמצן. Chamtsan. But the people of חמצן,
Chamtsan, okay, even if they're considered one city, good, they go a
thousand אמות amot. and they go another thousand and they're stuck over
there, okay? Because, so they don't get the benefit, you know, the
squaring off. Oh that's basically your point though. The squaring off only
worked for these people. It didn't work for these people.
Why? Because... because you are...
if you're no, it's nothing to do with squaring off. You're in
the city, you're considered that the whole city is one unit. But
if you start outside the city, right? It's not that the whole
city is one unit. So you wind up somewhere in the middle
there. You don't get to go all the way to the top.
Okay, so that's what תוספות, Tosafot. that's how תוספות Tosafot explains it.
Okay, so he says like this:
one minute. Okay, fine.
What?
So you have a different definition of the city for those who
begin inside and those who begin outside?
But no, remember that we anyway say when you begin outside, if
you don't, if the whole city isn't included in your 2,000 אמות,
amot. it counts against you. So this is really not saying anything
much different, you know, the same would be true and this is
really leading to the next answer of the גמרא. The same would
be true if this was an entire thing was a huge city
and ended in the middle of the city. You'd be stuck there.
Okay, but what makes this more interesting a little bit is is
that mostly you don't get you don't know you don't get act
like you're in a lot of open space. You like fud- you
don't get access to a lot of the city. At least in
the other scenario, you would have been in half the city. Okay,
so that's, so but essentially it's the idea that the whole city
was not included in your תחום, techum so you're stuck in the
middle. And that's really what the next answer's going to be in
the גמרא. רב דימי בר חיננא אמר אנשי עיר גדולה ואנשי עיר
קטנה הוי. Rav Dimi bar Chinnena amar anshei ir gedola v'anshei ir
ketana havei. Yeah, it was a simple case of big city, small
city, that the big city was not fully included in the תחום
techum of the small, and therefore you were stuck in the middle.
רב כהנא מתני הכי. Rav Kahana matni hachi. So that's how רב
כהנא Rav Kahana teaches the previous discussion. רב טביומי מתני הכי. Rav
Tavyumi matni hachi. Here's how רב טביומי Rav Tavyumi teaches. רב ספרא
ורב דימי בר חיננא. Rav Safra v'Rav Dimi bar Chinnena. It was
a debate of רב ספרא and רב דימי. חד אמר עיר שעשויה
כקשת הוי וחד אמר אנשי עיר קטנה ואנשי עיר גדולה הוי. Chad
amar ir she-asuyi k'keshet havei v'chad amar anshei ir ketana v'anshei ir
gedola havei. Okay, so again, it was the two opinions but it
was not clear who had said which. So basically we have this
interesting story of רבי allowing one direction and not the other. We
have no idea what it's about. One explanation having to do with
something political. The other explanation introducing this new idea of a retaining
wall. And the final two explanations basically similar to what we said
before about if the תחום techum, and city's included in the תחום,
techum it doesn't count against you. If the תחום ends in the
middle of the city, it does count against you. I have to
tell you a fast- a cute little thing that comes up in
תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot, said that some people had the גרסא girsa
in the גמרא ועוד התיר רבי. v'od hitir Rebbe. And in addition,
רבי was מתיר matir the following. So what does ועוד v'od mean?
This is basically this is actually a תוספתא. Tosefta. So תוספות Tosafot.
has some question like, was there a case before, not a case
before? But he has an interesting story. He says actually that was
a misread because the line before it said that a certain זקן,
zaken, because remember we had a whole משנה Mishna telling you that
you know, you know, you can trust anybody to tell you where
the תחום שבת techum Shabbat ended. So a certain זקן zaken told
רבי, he says, that what's the line? It says the first wide
line of תוספות, Tosafot, he says, or the last, like three lines
from the top of תוספות. ברואה זקן שבא לפני רבי ואמר לו
זכור אני שהיו בני מגדל יורדים למחטן לחמצן. Beruah zaken she-ba lifnei
Rebbe v'amar lo zakhur ani she-hayu bnei Migdal yordim l'Machtan... l'Chamtsan. I
remember that they used to go down here. עד החצר החיצונה הסמוכה
לגשר ועוד. Ad hachatzer hachitzona hasmucha l'gesher v'od. Until the courtyard that
was near the bridge and a little bit more. So he says
the word ועוד v'od was going on the previous line. They could
get up to here plus a little bit more. And then actually
got misread as being the beginning of the next sentence, ועוד התיר
רבי. v'od hitir Rebbe. But according to the תוספתא, Tosefta, it's actually
interesting that a certain person testified, I remember they used to go
up to here. And then רבי said, רבי came and he introduced
what the תחומים techumim would be and who would be able to,
and you know, גדר travel to חמצן Chamtsan and חמצן Chamtsan not
travel to גדר. Okay, so that's the end of that. And now
we've come to this משנה, Mishna, coming to wrap up this פרק,
perek, last משנה, Mishna, we've actually already quoted and discussed a lot
of it. So let's take a look. אנשי עיר גדולה מהלכים כל
עיר קטנה. Anshei ir gedola mahalchim kol ir ketana. The people of
a big city can go the whole small city. ואנשי, V'anshei, that's
our גרסא, girsa, and ואנשי עיר קטנה מהלכים כל עיר גדולה v'anshei
ir ketana mahalchim kol ir gedola and also small city go the
whole big city. כיצד? Keitzad? What's the example? מי שהיה בעיר גדולה
ונתן את עירובו בעיר קטנה. Mi she-hayah b'ir gedola v'natan et eruvo
b'ir ketana. If you were in the big city and put your
עירוב eruv in the small. או בעיר קטנה ונתן את עירובו בעיר
קטנה, בעיר גדולה, O b'ir ketana v'natan et eruvo b'ir ketana, b'ir
gedola, or in the small and put your עירוב eruv in the
big city, מהלכים את כולה וחוצה לה אלפיים אמה. mahalchim et kullah
v'chutz lah alpayim amot. You can go the whole thing. So basically
you can switch cities, allegiances of cities based on where you put
your עירוב eruv on שבת. Shabbat That doesn't sound like such a
big חידוש. chiddush. Again, what the גמרא suggest, you know, introduce as
another read of the משנה Mishna is, small city cannot go in
the big. big city, if their עירוב eruv ends in the middle,
that's case one of the משנה. Mishnah. Case two is unless the
following case where they actually put their עירוב eruv in the big
city. Fine. But the basic point is you put your עירוב eruv
in a different city you become part of the different city. Now
for us that's not does not sound like a big חידוש, chidush,
but we're actually going to find that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees.
So רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
אין לו אלא ממקום עירובו אלפיים אמה. ein lo ela mimakom eiruvo
alpayim amah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you do not get to
become part of a new city by putting your עירוב eruv there.
And if you put your עירוב eruv in a city you only
get 2000 אמות. So, in order to get the whole city, right
remember we talked before to get the whole city it had to
all be within your 2000 אמות, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says to
be a member of a new city and to get the whole
city, you have to actually have stayed there when שבת Shabbat begins.
But if you just put your עירוב eruv there, you put your
bread there, that's not enough to make you a real member of
a whole city. The idea that the whole city doesn't count against
you and it's your 4 אמות is only said for real city
dwellers, not for virtual city dwellers. So if you put your עירוב
eruv there, you don't get the whole city. You have to actually
have been there when שבת Shabbat began. מערב ברגלו? me'arev beraglo? Yeah,
מערב ברגלו. me'arev beraglo.
I thought that made that was dependent on the מחלוקת machlokes we
had
before about whether להקל lehakel or not. Okay, so fundamentally using the
bread is a קולא, kula, but there are times where we're not
so according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we don't give it all
of the status and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says this idea is
a big leniency that the whole city doesn't count against you. And
that's only said for a person that's a real member of the
city and not by virtually being there by putting your bread there.
That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said. So אמר להם amar lahem
and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to
them אי אתם מודים לי בנותן עירובו במערה שאין לו אלא ממקום
עירובו אלפיים אמה? ee atem modim lee benosen eiruvo beme'arah she'ein lo
ela mimakom eiruvo alpayim amah? Wouldn't you agree with me that if
somebody put their עירוב eruv in a in a cave that you
would have to you would not get the whole cave, you'd only
get the 2000 אמה? amah? אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said
back to him אימתי, eimasi, when is that true? בזמן שאין בה
דיורין, bezman she'ein bah diyurin, if it's that it's not a city,
there's nobody living there. אבל יש בה דיורין, aval yesh bah diyurin,
if there are people actually living there, then מהלך את כולה וחוצה
לה אלפיים אמה. mehalech es kullah vechutza lah alpayim amah. No, you
get to go the entire cave and outside of it 2000 אמה.
amah. So we don't agree with you. When it's actually if it's
just a cave, fine. But if it's actually a real city, then
putting your עירוב eruv there makes you a member of the city.
נמצא קלתה ממעל גבה. nimtza kaltah mima'al gabah. It's more lenient if
you put your עירוב eruv in the cave than if you put
it on top of the cave. Because in the cave, if there's
people living in it, you get the entire cave, right?
So here you've got
right, here's your cave, right? Whatever, here's your cave and here's the
ground on top of it. So inside the cave you have all
these people living, right? So if you put your עירוב eruv here,
you get to go the entire length of the cave and 2000
אמות in all directions. If however you put your עירוב eruv up
here, you're not in the middle of a city. So you only
get to go 2000 אמה, amah, but you do not get the
entire length of the cave. So if you put your עירוב eruv
in the cave and there are people living in it, it's going
to be more lenient than on top of the cave.
Because the cave is like a big house. Right.
So so right. So למודה שאמרו lemodeh she'amru now, although there was
that debate about whether you get the city or not by putting
your עירוב eruv there, everybody agrees that if you started outside of
the city, then this is the line we've quoted before, and you're
measuring and you and you get into the city, נותנים לו אלפיים
אמה שאפילו סוף מידתו כלה במערה. nosnim lo alpayim amah she'afilu sof
midaso kalah beme'arah. There, even if your 2000 אמות ended in the
cave—and now you see why it said cave because that was the
context they were talking about—and even if there were people in the
cave, you stop where you stop. Okay, so this is a nice
bringing together of the ideas which is: when does the whole city
count not count against you? Certainly if you start in the city,
it doesn't count against you. If you start outside the city, that's
the last line, then it does count against you if you end
in the middle of the city. If your 2000 end in the
middle. What we said before this was that if the whole city
is within your 2000, it doesn't count against you. But what if
you put your עירוב eruv, in the city and you don't start
there? And that is the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
the חכמים chachamim that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you cannot be
considered part of the city unless you literally start in the city
yourself. Okay? But the חכמים chachamim agree that the city does count
against you when you started outside and you ended in the middle
of a city. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Top of
ס"א ע"ב. samech aleph amud beis. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Said Rav Yehuda in the name of
Shmuel. שבת בעיר, shavas be'ir, if somebody actually sort of began שבת,
Shabbos you know, physical meaning your own physical presence, not your עירוב,
eruv בעיר חרבה, be'ir chreivah, in a in a desolate city. Okay,
so nobody is living there anymore. But it used to be a
ghost town. Thank you. It used to be a city. So is
that count as enough of a city? Okay, so לרבנן, leRabanan, מהלך
את כולה וחוצה לה אלפיים אמה. mehalech es kullah vechutza lah alpayim
amah. So there you would be able to go the entire city
and outside of it 2000 אמה. amah. That even a ghost town
actually counts as a city that you get the entire town. הניח
את עירובו. heniyach es eiruvo.
Okay, so how did they get that?
Okay, it's going to be debated. Let's take a look. Okay, now
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* by the way says that it is talking about
that you actually it actually is surrounded by walls. Okay, so let
me read and then I'll step back again. הניח את עירובו *Heiniach
et eruvo* בעיר חרבה *be'ir chareiva*, if however you leave your eruv
in a desolate city, אין לו ממקום עירובו אלא אלפיים אמה *ein
lo mimakom eruvo ella alpaim amah*, then you only get where your
eruv was actually placed. So what he is saying is the following.
He is saying like this. Rabbi Akiva's got a little confusing, okay.
I actually have to make a chart, I've been avoiding making charts.
Okay, but anyway, here is the point. Okay, here you have a
עיר ir, *ir* which is inhabited, okay. That's one scenario. You have
another scenario which is a עיר חרבה *ir chareiva* but it has
walls, or another way of just saying it is like the like
let's say a empty מערה me'arah
*me'ara*,
okay, which also has walls, okay. So we will make those separate
because this at least used to be a city. Okay fine, and
then let's say you're by yourself. Okay we don't even need to
say you're by yourself. Okay, so what happens is is that the
Rabbis say like this. So, I don't know, this is going to
get way too confusing. But anyway, it's the רבנן Rabbanan. *Rabanan*. I
know, I know, it's going to get too confusing because I want
to do yourself, yourself, and then and then your eruv. So Rabbi
Akiva says let's just talk about what Rabbi Akiva would say. Rabbi
Akiva says the only time you get the entire two thousand the
entire city is in this case, okay. So Rabbi Akiva that's the
entire the only time. You yourself are there and you're in an
inhabited city, okay. If you put your eruv there it doesn't work,
and certainly the other cases are going to be worse. So for
Rabbi Akiva, so your R equals Rabbi Akiva, okay. For the רבנן
Rabbanan *Rabanan*, right, we know that they say that if you put
your eruv in an inhabited city it does work, okay. So certainly
if you yourself are in an inhabited city it does work. They
also said in the Mishna, right, so if you so it does
work. They also said that if you're in the empty מערה *me'ara*,
if you're in the empty cave, okay, there they said that actually
it does not work to put your eruv in the empty cave
because it's not an inhabited city because you know that's that's not
really a city. So the question is going to be according to
the רבנן Rabbanan. *Rabanan*, what happens if you yourself are in the
are in the empty cave but it's surrounded by walls?
Which would be an עיר חרבה *ir chareiva* then?
Okay, maybe, maybe not. What if you're in the עיר חרבה *ir
chareiva* and it's surrounded by walls, right? Do you get a place
that you are surrounded by walls or not? So I'll just jump
ahead and tell you that the assumption is that if you yourself
are in a place surrounded by walls according to the רבנן *Rabanan*,
all the then that all counts as like ארבע אמות *arba amot*,
okay, you actually are okay, okay, because you yourself were there and
it's surrounded by walls. I think Rabbi Akiva agrees to those as
well. The question is going to be this, okay. What is going
to be the story with just your eruv? Is it like the
מערה *me'ara* because it's empty so even though it's surrounded by walls
it's just your eruv, or is it like the עיר *ir* because
it started off as an עיר *ir*? And this is going to
be the issue that's going to be debated. I don't know if
that made it any clearer. The basic point is that according to
the רבנן *Rabanan*, if it's you yourself and you're surrounded by walls
it works. If it's your eruv and if it's in a city
it works. What if it's in a city that is חרבה *chareiva*,
okay? And maybe that, you know, maybe that's a much easier way
of saying this. Okay, so like this: if it's yourself plus walls,
like you start in a house or wherever you start, you get
the entire space of the of the area surrounded by a house,
okay. Then that works, then you get the that that works. If
it's your eruv plus city, that works, okay. So if it's an
eruv plus walls without a city, that's the case of the מערה
*me'ara*, it does not work. What about, okay, what about if it's
an eruv plus a עיר חרבה *ir chareiva*?
Is it like this or is it like this? That's the question.
Okay, so let's take a look. I hope that wasn't too confusing.
Rabbi Yehuda is consistent with, like, you know, in some ways Mishnas
of enough, right? Right.
Yeah, let's let's stay focused, Michael. Okay, so it says like this.
So he says that if it's in a חרבה *chareiva*, עיר חרבה
*ir chareiva*, it's like being surrounded by walls and it's just your
eruv, it doesn't work. רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer* אחד שבת
ואחד הניח *echad Shabbat ve'echad heiniach*, whether you actually were in that
desolate city, that ghost town, or whether you placed your eruv, מהלכת
כולה וחוצה לה אלפיים אמה mehalekhet kulah vekhutzah alpaim ama, *mehalechet kulla
vechotza la alpaim amah*, you get the whole city. So מיתיבי *Meitivei*,
I'll ask you on this. אמר להן רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Amar
lahen Rabbi Akiva* אי אתם מודים לי בנותן את עירובו במערה bim'arah
שאין לו ממקום עירובו אלא אלפיים אמה *ei attem modim li benoten
et eruvo beme'ara she'ein lo mimakom eruvo ella alpaim amah*? Don't you
agree that in a cave you don't get the whole cave? אמרו
לו *Amru lo* אימתי *eimatai*, when is that? בזמן שאין בה דיורין
*bezman she'ein bah diyurin*, if nobody is living in it. הא יש
בה דיורין *Ha yesh bah diyurin* so the Gemara says so you
see הא באינה בת דיורין מודי modei, ליה *ha be'eina bat diyurin
modi leh*. So it says look, the רבנן *Rabanan* say if it's
the case of the מערה *me'ara* it does not work, and why
do they say it doesn't work? They say nobody's living there, so
your עירוב eruv plus walls does not enough. So isn't a desolate
city the exact same thing? Right? Nobody is living there, so the
גמרא says מה אין בה דיורין? mai ein bah diyurin? What does
it mean nobody lives there? אין ראויה לדיורה. ein re'uyah lediyurah. It
means it's not fit for living, fit for habitation. But a ghost
town is better. So the exact point is exactly this. Is this
case of the of the עיר חריבה ir hareva like the case
of the מערה or not? Is it easier or is it harder?
Exactly. Okay. So the גמרא says
so where at? אין ראויה... ein re'uyah... תא שמע, tashma, come and
hear. שבת בעיר shavat be'ir אפילו היא גדולה כאנטיוכיא, afilu hi gedolah
k'Antiocha, if you spent if you actually were physically in a city,
even if it's a huge city like Antioch במערה אפילו היא כמערת
צדקיהו, afilu hi k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu, or you started שבת in a cave,
even like the cave of צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, you know the tunnels of
צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu that you know, used to escape ירושלים, Yerushalayim, מלך יהודה.
melech Yehudah. מהלכת כולה וחוצה לה אלפיים אמה, you have the entire
cave, the entire city. קתני עיר דומיא דמערה. katani ir dumya d'me'arah.
So it said a city similar to a cave. מה מערה חריבה,
mah me'arah hareva, the same way a cave is desolate, אף עיר
חריבה, af ir hareva,
even a city would be considered like if it were even if
it were a desert city. ושבת אין, veshavat in, and it says
because you start שבת there, that's why it counts. אבל הניח לא,
aval hiniakh lo, not if you just place it there. It's funny
it had to go to the city example, could have just said
look, it says by the cave only but the reason it says
the cave isn't a good point
is the cave was never ראויה לדיורה, re'uyah lediyurah, so it wants
to have a case of a city that was a ghost town.
So it says ah, city like the cave, nobody is living there
and even so, it's only when you yourself start שבת there. So
you see that a desolate city is like a cave. So the
גמרא says מני, mani, who is this going like? אילימא רבי עקיבא,
ileima Rabbi Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, who always has
a problem, so מה עיר חריבה, mah ir hareva, he wouldn't have
had to say a city like a cave. אפילו ישיבה נמי, afilu
yeshivah nami, even if it was an inhabited city, then he, רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, would have said you needed to have started שבת
in the city.
Anyway, so by assuming that the city means a desolate city, we're
saying it can't be רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva. then there's no חידוש.
chiddush. אלא
לאו רבנן, ela lav Rabbanan, it's the רבנן. וטעמא, veta'ama, so they're
talking about a desolate city, and the reason you get the city
is דשבת, deshavat, because you actually began שבת there. אין אבל הניח,
in aval hiniakh, if you just put your עירוב eruv there, לא,
it would not work. גמרא says no. לא תימא עיר דומיא דמערה,
lo teima ir dumya d'me'arah, don't say because of the juxtaposition of
city and cave we mean a desolate city and therefore this is
your חידוש chiddush that a desolate city you have to actually physically
be there. No. אלא אימא מערה דומיא דעיר, ela eima me'arah dumya
d'ir, say the reverse. The cave is like the city scenario. מה
עיר ישיבה, mah ir yeshivah, the same way the עיר is inhabited,
אף מערה ישיבה, af me'arah yeshivah, even the cave is inhabited. Okay.
So therefore it says if you have an inhabited city or an
inhabited cave and you start שבת in it, you get the whole
thing. So who's the one that says you have to actually physically
start שבת in an inhabited city? That is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva
ורבי עקיבא היא, veRabbi Akiva hi, דאמר אין לו ממקום עירובו אלא
אלפיים אמה, de'amar ein lo mimakom eruvo ela alpaim ama, that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva normally says that if you have your עירוב eruv
in a city you only get two thousand אמות. ובשבת, u'veShabbat, but
when you rest in the city, when you begin in the city,
מודי, he agrees. Okay, so it says the case of the cave
is like the city case, it's talking about inhabited, this is position
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and that's why it says you have
to start שבת in the city, in the cave. Now, wait a
minute. So the גמרא says והא כמערת צדקיהו קתני, veha k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu
katani,
but it says like the tunnels of צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, they weren't inhabited.
That was in the ברייתא. It says even if they're as big
as the tunnels of צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu. So the גמרא says כמערת צדקיהו
ולא כמערת צדקיהו. k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu velo k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu. Yeah, like them, but
not totally like them. כמערת צדקיהו גדולה, k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu gedolah, they're very,
very large. ולא כמערת צדקיהו, velo k'me'arat Tzidkiyahu, we don't mean literally
like them. דאילו התם חריבה והכא ישיבה, de'ilu hatam hareva vehakha yeshivah,
there they were non-inhabited and here we're talking about a scenario they
are inhabited. Okay. So we don't have a resolution about this. So
again, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. is very limited on when you're entitled
to the whole city. Only if you are a city dweller or
if you actually start שבת there. The רבנן is more what we're
used to, that you can get the whole city. One scenario you
can get the whole city is if it's included in your two
thousand אמות. The other is if you put your עירוב eruv there.
Okay, so then you actually can get the whole city if you
put your עירוב eruv there. Also, however, if you put your עירוב
eruv just where there are walls, you do not.
That's for everybody. So either if you want to get sort of
more than your ארבע אמות, if it's a city, your עירוב eruv?
is enough. If it's yourself, then any place that you're surrounded by
walls. Those are the two models for the רבנן. Okay. And the
question is an עירוב eruv in a desolate city surrounded by walls,
right? Is that like this, which needs to be you yourself, or
is it like the city case where it could even be your
עירוב? eruv Okay. So now let's just see how the גמרא resolves
this.
מר יהודה Mar Yehudah מר יהודה Mar Yehuda found the people of
מפרכתא Mafrachta דקא מותבי עירווייהו de-ka mosvei eruvai-hu בי כנישתא דבי אגוגבא.
bei k'nishta de-vei Agogva. By the way, I should mention that one
thing interesting about עירובין Eruvin is you have a lot of case
law. You know, have you noticed that? Like a lot of real
stories about how this stuff played out. Anyway, so he found the
people of מפרכתא Mafrachta were putting their עירוב eruv, in the synagogue
of of this of the of the house of אגוגבא, Agogva, okay.
אמר להו Amar le-hu so he said to them, גבו בתפאי כי
היכי דלישתרו לכו טפאי. gavu batfei ki hechi di-lish-ru le-chu tfei. Put
it more inside so you can get more into the city, which
means what?
Which means that basically
here I don't know let's say outside of the city limits or
into the next city was this בית הכנסת, Beit HaKnesset, okay, and
they put their עירוב eruv there. Now that is a scenario of
your עירוב, eruv. right, in a place with... wait a minute, hold
on, let me just double check because actually I think it was
a city, excuse me. It wasn't out in the middle.
One minute, one minute.
Isn't a בית כנסת? Beit
Knesset? Anyone living
in there?
Yeah,
one minute.
One minute, just one sec.
One minute.
One minute, that almost makes it sound... just for one second. Makes
it
sound...
Okay, yeah, I guess this is just because... okay, fine. Okay, the
point basically being, I'm sorry, that this is this is like the
city because the issue is that people are still like living here.
It doesn't matter that apparently it doesn't matter, I'm just seeing from
רש"י, it doesn't matter that this is actually part of the city
or not. The fact that there actually are people living here allows
you to put your עירוב eruv and be considered part of... in
the בית כנסת? Beit Knesset? So yeah this would have the issue
similar to the עירוב. eruv It seems from רש"י that in the
בית כנסת Beit Knesset here, I'll make you a Jewish star, a
בית כנסת. Beit Knesset.
Okay, anyway, because there are people that actually are, you know, living
in there, it's considered like the city. This is only if it's
like completely empty, like the walls are completely desolate. But that actually
has the status of like putting it, you know, putting it in
the city. So the point is they would put their עירוב eruv.
here, okay, and they put it let's say at the edge. So
he said look, he said we keep being חושש choshesh for, you
know, for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva, And for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva
even though that's considered to be like an עיר, right, in order
for you to be to get the entire space, right, you have
to actually physically be there yourself. The only case רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva, allows is with yourself. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the only case
he allows is you plus the city. Okay, so דיירי, dayarei, like
the people are living there. Okay, so according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, right, that wouldn't work. You have to be you yourself even
though people are living there. So he says put your עירוב eruv
more inside, more towards the back, so you can get further in
that direction. And he was being חושש choshesh for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, and that wasn't enough. One minute. אמר להו Amar le-hu גבו
בתפאי, gavu batfei, put it more inside, כי היכי דלישתרו לכו טפאי,
ki hechi di-lish-ru le-chu tfei, that more should be allowed to you,
you should be able to get... oops, you should be able to
get more into more into the city. So
אמר ליה רבא, amar leih Rava, so רבא Rava said, פגע בעירובין,
pag'a ba-eiruvin, you are sort of disagreeing with the... I'm sorry, this
thing is just being crazy... you're disagreeing with the Rabbis when it
comes to עירובין. eruvin. לית לך להא דרבי עקיבא, leit lach l-had
d-Rabbi Akiva, nobody is concerned with the position of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva. you don't have to be concerned with רבי עקיבא. And if
you look at רש"י, רש"י says, דקיימא לן הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב.
de-kaim lan halakha ke-divrei ha-mekel be-eruv. And right, the similar תוספות, לית
לך להא דרבי עקיבא דקיימא לן כדברי המיקל בעירוב. leit lach l-had
d-Rabbi Akiva de-kaim lan ke-divrei ha-mekel be-eruv. So according to them it's
not just in a local point, it's again reaffirming, which by the
way in the גמרא was not everybody's opinion, it was one position,
but reaffirming this idea that we always go leniently by עירוב. eruv
So that means that So that means that basically, and this is
of course this is how we rule, that if you're yourself and
walls, even if there's nobody living there, if it's an עירוב eruv
and a city, then if it's a city and people are living
there, then you don't need to be yourself, you can become part
of the city. Not exactly clear how we פסק'ן pasken if it's
a ghost town. Okay, maybe we would also say הלכה כדברי המיקל,
halacha k'divrei hameikel, okay, which one would that fall into? But the
point here about the בית כנסת beis knesses which is important to
note, which got me sort of stumped for a minute, is that
this is being treated like a city because since people live there,
even though it's not a whole city, once it's a place that
is being inhabited, the key here is that it's uninhabited, and city
maybe is confusing, עירוב eruv plus inhabited, that makes it a lot
clearer. Okay, this is uninhabited. Okay, so that's the basic difference. So
because this is inhabited, according to, you know, putting your עירוב eruv,
there makes you as if you are one of the inhabitants. So
that's the basic position of the חכמים Chachamim that, you know, that
any place that is inhabited, if your עירוב eruv. is there, it
makes you one of the inhabitants, and then you get the entire
city or the entire space surrounded by walls. And the only issue
is if it's uninhabited, then to get the entire city, you actually
have to be there yourself.
The question is between uninhabited and uninhabitable. So like, you know, let's
say...
Well, that's the debate of the ghost town. Okay, that's exactly the
debate of the ghost town.
I mean, you can still have a pretty intact ghost town, but
if it looks like half the walls are falling apart...
Okay, then everybody would agree. The whole argument about the ghost town
was that it was inhabitable. Okay, but that's the issue. All right.
So we basically פסק'ן where you put your עירוב, eruv if it's
a place that is inhabited, then it's like you're one of the
inhabitants, and you get either the whole city or, if it's not
a city, at least you get the area that is surrounded by
walls. הדרן עלך כיצד מערבין, Hadran alach Keitzad Me'arvin, that is the
end of that פרק perek which, as I said, was a very
fun פרק. perek. It was about עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. Now we're
going to get back to עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzeros, which is definitely
more challenging, and we get to a very important discussion in the
next משנה Mishna that leads to all these interesting issues about if
you would, inclusion and exclusion. So let's take a look at the
beginning of the next משנה Mishna which talks about the actual making
of an עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzeros. הדר עם העכו"ם בחצר, Hadar im
ha'akum bechatzer, if you're living with a non-Jew in your courtyard, או
עם מי שאינו מודה בעירוב, o im mi she'eino modeh b'eruv, or
you're somebody in your courtyard doesn't believe in עירוב. eruv. Now, who
would that be? Presumably, it's a Jew. So it's either a צדוקי
Tzadoki or a כותי. Kuti. Okay, so those are the two Samaritans.
What?
They weren't around then.
הקראים Hakaraim weren't around yet. Okay. So it's either Samaritans or Sadducees.
All right. So הרי זה אוסר עליו. harei zeh oser alav. This
person makes it forbidden to you. Basically, means that this is, by
the way, very important because we'll see in the גמרא different explanations
for this. But the thing that you have to appreciate, and I
sent out a few weeks ago a nice article by Charlotte Fonrobert
on עירובין, Eruvin, where this is the point she really emphasizes, you
know, that the idea of עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros is very much
about creating a sense of a cohesive community. Everybody joins together, you're
all unified, it creates a sense of a community which on the
one way makes boundaries with the other courtyard that wasn't part of
your עירוב eruv and, you know, so you're distinct, but everybody at
least here is unified and brought together. So what if somebody
cannot be seen or doesn't want to be seen by the rabbis
as part of that community? A non-Jew or somebody that doesn't buy
into this whole idea of עירוב. eruv So can they contribute to
the עירוב eruv. and all be brought together? In ways, they are
excluded from the עירוב eruv community, either they're not Jewish so they're
fundamentally excluded or they exclude themselves, they don't buy into the whole
idea of עירוב. eruv So when you have dealing with them, הרי
זה אוסר עליו, harei zeh oser alav, they make it all forbidden
to you. You can't make, according to the simple sense of this
משנה, Mishna, you can't make an עירוב eruv, in the courtyard. You're
stuck because they can't be part of the community. Now the גמרא
is going to introduce an idea that you can solve it by
renting the space from them because, you know, everybody agrees, you know,
whether you believe in the religion or not in the religion, we
all believe in business. So if you rent the space, then the
rest of the people in the courtyard really have rights to it
and you, the non-Jew or the apostate, for this שבת don't have
rights to your חלק, chelek, so you don't
have, your membership or non-membership is irrelevant.
Okay, but without renting, you cannot become part of the עירוב eruv?
and therefore you create a problem. Let's keep on reading a little
bit.
It's not like he's there for...
No, no, no, he has one of the houses of the courtyard.
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says לעולם אינו אוסר עד שיהיו
שני ישראלים אוסרים זה על זה. le'olam eino oser ad she'yehu shnei
Yisraelim osrim zeh al zeh. It's not a problem unless you have
two Jews in a courtyard. But if you only have one Jew
in a courtyard, it's not a problem. Now, that's a little bit
bizarre. You would think the more Jews in the courtyard, the better.
You would also think that if there's only one Jew in a
courtyard, then who's he making the עירוב, what does it mean? One
Jew in the courtyard and there are ten non-Jews or ten כותים
Kutim or whatever, and he can carry without making an עירוב?
Well, if he's the only Jew that has jurisdiction over that courtyard...
No, they all, the other ones do too. In practical terms, this
courtyard is shared by
the other
ten people. I know, but it's a little funny because practically you
have all these different people using the courtyard, and that's not conceived
as properly—I know, I'm just saying we'll have to see that. So
one is a question about why is one Jew better than two
Jews? And number two is, in a practical sense, a courtyard that's
shared by multiple people, that that should be a non-issue is a
funny idea, but that's what the משנה *Mishnah* implies. So we'll see
more about that in the גמרא *Gemara*. And now we have a
story about an—again talking about case law, an actual story. אמר רבן
גמליאל *Amar Rabban Gamliel*, מעשה בצדוקי אחד *Maaseh bitzeduki echad*, there was
a story of a case about a Sadducee, שהיה דר עמנו במבוי
*shehayah dar immanu bamavoi*, that he was part of, you know—not courtyard
but the מבוי *mavoi*, like a courtyard that opened into an alleyway,
בירושלים *biYerushalayim*. ואמר לנו אבא *Ve'amar lanu Abba*, and our father said
to us, מהרו והוציאו את הכלים למבוי עד שלא יוציא ויאסר עליכם
*Maharu vehotziu et hakelim lamavoi ad shelo yotzi veye'aser aleichem*. Go quickly,
take all your vessels out into the—into the מבוי *mavoi* so that
he doesn't take his stuff out and make it forbidden on you.
Now what the heck is going on here? So what רש"י *Rashi*
says is that he is assuming that a צדוקי *Tzeduki*, somebody who
is not מודה בעירוב *modeh be'eruv*, is not like the non-Jew. The
non-Jew, if you want to make an עירוב *eruv*, you have to
rent his space. Again, not in the משנה *Mishnah*. But the צדוקי
*Tzeduki*, if you want an עירוב *eruv*, it's enough for him to
be מבטל רשות *mevattel reshut*. He's Jewish, he just doesn't buy in.
So he can't be an active member of the עירוב *eruv*, but
he can say, you know what, I waive my rights. That he
can say. You don't have to actually have a formal rental agreement.
On the one hand you don't need that much, on the other
hand he can't actually be an active member of the עירוב *eruv*,
but what he can say is, I waive my rights. The problem
of saying I waive my rights is that he can reclaim his
rights. So that's the issue. So it worked by him waiving his
rights. It's not a complete problem, but we have to stop him
from reclaiming his rights. So therefore what we do is, when שבת
*Shabbat* begins, we go out there and we assert our rights in
the courtyard so he can't go ahead and change his mind. Like
it's—if you were מפקיר *mafkir* something and before anybody picked it up,
you grabbed it back. So you don't want that to happen. So
we have to grab what he was מפקיר *mafkir*. Every שבת *Shabbat*?
Every שבת *Shabbat* we would have to do this. Okay. How does
that work, though?
Like how do they prevent him
from—no, after presumably they've asserted their rights, he can now come and
use it during the שבת *Shabbat*, but after they've already established that
for this שבת *Shabbat* we are the ones that have, you know,
rights over this space. So it's like if you were מפקיר *mafkir*
an object and I picked it up, if you picked it up
afterwards it would still be mine. So now the courtyard isn't there
at—from perpetuity, but for the purpose of this שבת *Shabbat*, this כותי
*Kutti* said I waive my rights, and if we then showed that
we were taking sort of—asserting our rights to it for שבת *Shabbat*,
then he's not in a position to reclaim his rights for the
שבת *Shabbat*. That's at least the assumption. So it has a lot
of things that are not in this משנה *Mishnah* that are being
assumed. A צדוקי *Tzeduki* is different than a non-Jew, maybe even different
than a כותי *Kutti*, we can discuss that.
You don't have to rent it from him, which wasn't in the
משנה *Mishnah* anyway, the renting. He can waive his rights, but you
have to make sure he doesn't—he doesn't reclaim them. Okay, let's just
read the other case. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehudah omer*, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehudah* said, בלשון אחר *belashon acher*, he had a different version
of the story. מהרו ועשו צרכיכם במבוי עד שלא יוציא ויאסר עליכם
*Maharu ve'asu tzorcheichem bamavoi ad shelo yotzi veye'aser aleichem*. Take care of
anything you need to do in the מבוי *mavoi* until he
goes—because he'll come out—he'll come out and he'll make it forbidden. And
the way the גמרא *Gemara* explains the difference is that he actually
says that even after you've used the courtyard, he can reclaim his
rights. He can always reclaim his rights. So basically it's גורנישט העלפן
*gornisht helfn*. Even if he waives his rights, all you can do
is use it until he changes his mind. So what he actually
said is, better—better make the best out of it now, because as
soon as he changes his mind you're in trouble. So what we
have here is a couple of fascinating things. A non-Jew or מי
שאינו מודה בעירוב *mi she'eino modeh be'eruv* cannot be an active part
of the—of the עירוב *eruv*. What can they do? Not really spelled
out at all in the משנה *Mishnah*. We'll see in the גמרא
*Gemara* that from a non-Jew you can rent it. From a—somebody who's
not מודה בעירוב *modeh be'eruv* you might have another alternative, which is
to let him waive his rights. And then what's being debated here
is after he's waived his rights, is there a way to secure
that for all of שבת *Shabbat* or is he always in a
position to, you know, reassert his rights and to reverse it? And
then we also have the really fascinating issue of the difference between
two Jews and one Jew and how that's going to play out.
So it's going to be a lot of דפים *dappim* and we
will pick up with this tomorrow.